<doc>
  <head>
    <title>Mibble TODO-List</title>
  </head>

  <body>

    <h1>Known Issues</h1>

    <p>This is a list of the known issues as of the release of version
    <param name="version" /> (<param name="date" />). The most
    up-to-date version of this list is available from the
    <ref url="http://savannah.nongnu.org/bugs/?group=mibble">project
    bug tracker</ref>.</p>

    <list>
      <item>
        <text>There are currently no known issues.</text>
      </item>
    </list>


    <h1>Suggested Improvements</h1>

    <p>This is a list of the suggested improvements as of the release
    of version <param name="version" /> (<param name="date" />). The
    most up-to-date version of this list is available from the
    <ref url="http://savannah.nongnu.org/bugs/?group=mibble">project
    bug tracker</ref>.</p>

    <list>
      <item>
        <title>Support strict SMIv1 and SMIv2 parsing</title>
        <text>When parsing SMIv1 files, no symbols or constructs from
        SMIv2 should be available. The opposite goes for SMIv2 files.
        <ref bug="4367" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Create unit tests</title>
        <text>All the source code should be tested automatically
        through JUnit or a similar tool. This is a minor issue,
        however, as the complete library is always tested with all
        the IETF MIB files on each build. <ref bug="4368" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Add SNMP client capabilities</title>
        <text>The Mibble library currently has no support for SNMP
        agents or clients. It is possible to integrate with SNMP4J or
        the WestHawk SNMP stack to provide this.
        <ref bug="6317" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Validate SEQUENCE element types</title>
        <text>The types in a <code>SEQUENCE</code> should be validated
        against their counterparts if also defined separately.
        <ref bug="6547" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Add object serialization</title>
        <text>There is currently no easy way to store the state of a
        loaded Mib, so the same files have to be parsed every time
        which may be time consuming. By adding object serialization or
        similar this might be faster. <ref bug="6960" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Add error recovery for missing imports</title>
        <text>Currently Mibble reports errors and fails loading of MIB
        files containing symbols that have not been properly imported.
        <ref bug="7113" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Support rarely used ASN.1 types and constraints</title>
        <text>There are several rarely used ASN.1 type and constraint
        constructs that have not been implemented in Mibble. These
        include SET, SET OF, ANY and the ENUMERATED types. None of
        these are used in SNMP MIB files. <ref bug="8093" /></text>
      </item>
    </list>

  </body>
</doc>
