<doc>
  <head>
    <title>Mibble Features</title>
  </head>

  <body>

    <h1>Existing Features</h1>

    <p>This is a summary of the features currently present in
    Mibble.</p>

    <list>
      <item>
        <title>Full support for both SMIv1 and SMIv2</title>
        <text>The library contains full support for both SNMP
        SMI versions and comes bundled with all the standard
        IANA and IETF MIB files.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Support for much of the ASN.1 syntax</title>
        <text>Mibble not only supports parsing SNMP MIB files,
        but also parses generic ASN.1 files (with some
        exceptions). This makes it possible to use the library
        in non-SNMP contexts as well.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Proper import &amp; symbol handling</title>
        <text>Each referenced module is imported either from
        the bundled MIB files or from an externally supplied
        source (filesystem or URL). Symbols can also be
        prefixed with their module names to avoid possible
        naming conflicts.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Full access to all type information</title>
        <text>All the type and value information from the files
        are available to an application through public methods
        in the library. A complete in-memory structure is created
        for quick access to all this information.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Detailed and precise error messages</title>
        <text>Messages generated when an error is found always
        describe the problem with all required details. Error
        messages also contains a short except from the MIB
        file.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Complete source code available</title>
        <text>The source code for the complete library is freely
        available under either the GNU GPL or a commercial license.
        This makes it easy to check details in the implementation or
        to make small adjustments.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Commercial license available for proprietary software</title>
        <text>The GNU GPL licence does not allow distribution of
        products based on Mibble unless they are licensed under the
        GNU GPL themselves. A commercial license containing the full
        source code for Mibble is therefore available for sale.</text>
      </item>
    </list>


    <h1>Upcoming Features</h1>

    <p>No commitment has been made regarding which new features will
    be present in future releases. See the
    <ref file="bugs.xml">TODO-list</ref> for a the currently known
    future improvements.</p>

  </body>
</doc>
