<doc>
  <head>
    <title>Mibble Version Information</title>
  </head>

  <body>

    <h1>Version <param name="version"/> (<param name="date"/>):</h1>

    <list>
      <item>
        <title>Updated to version 1.4 of Grammatica</title>
        <text>The Grammatica library distributed with Mibble has been
        updated to version 1.4 (from 1.3). The build file has been
        simplified as a result of this. (Bug #5000)</text>
      </item>
    </list>


    <h1>Version 2.1 (2003-08-22):</h1>

    <list>
      <item>
        <title>Corrected MIB symbol value search</title>
        <text>Searching for MIB symbols by value never returned any 
        results in the previous version. Thanks to Nigel Mellor for
        finding and fixing this. (Bug #4893)</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Updated to version 1.3 of Grammatica</title>
        <text>The Grammatica library distributed with Mibble has been
        updated to version 1.3 (from 1.2). Minor changes have been 
        made to the parser to accomodate this. (Bug #4903)</text>
      </item>
    </list>


    <h1>Version 2.0 (2003-07-19):</h1>

    <list>
      <item>
        <title>Complete rewrite with API and name change</title>
        <text>The project has been renamed to Mibble, and the library 
        has been completely rewritten from scratch. The API:s have
        also been replaced to correct a number of serious flaws in 
        the previous design.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added complete support for SNMPv2 and SNMPv3</title>
        <text>All types and constructs in SNMPv2 and SNMPv3 are now 
        supported.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added a real MIB import mechanism</title>
        <text>Symbol imports are now handled by reading and parsing
        the MIB file. Standard IANA and IETF MIB files have been 
        added to the JAR library, in order to always have these 
        imports available.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added full access to all type information</title>
        <text>All of the type information can now be easily accessed
        through methods in the type classes.</text>
      </item>
      
      <item>
        <title>Added syntactical and semantical error recovery</title>
        <text>The MIB parser now attempts to recover from errors in
        the MIB file. All encountered errors are available after the
        parsing is complete. This change was made available by using
        Grammatica instead of JavaCC to generate the parser.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added warnings for wrong identifier case</title>
        <text>A warning is now issued if the first character in a 
        type identifier is lower-case, or if the first character in a 
        value identifier is upper-case.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added HTML release notes</title>
        <text>The release notes are now generated to both text and
        HTML format from an XML representation.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Changed parser generator to Grammatica</title>
        <text>The JavaCC parser generator has been replaced with
        Grammatica. This was done as JavaCC isn't free software, and
        Grammatica was chosen as it provides a simple grammar syntax,
        a decent parsing and analysis framework, and very high 
        quality error handling.</text>
      </item>
      
      <item>
        <title>Removed the old symbol tree model</title>
        <text>The symbol tree model has been removed as it was not
        compatible with the new API:s.</text>
      </item>
    </list>


    <h1>Version 1.2 (2003-03-27):</h1>

    <list>
      <item>
        <title>Relicensing to GPL + linking exception</title>
        <text>Relicensed all the source code to GPL plus a linking 
        exception. See the new LICENSE.txt file for details.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Removed JavaCC requirement from Ant build file</title>
        <text>Removed the strict dependency of JavaCC from Ant build 
        file (build.xml). The JavaCC parser generator will be replaced 
        in a future version of the library.</text>
      </item>
    </list>

 
    <h1>Version 1.1 (2003-01-06):</h1>

    <list>
      <item>
        <title>Updated MIB syntax to SNMPv2</title>
        <text>The MIB file parser can now handle several new macros, 
        such as MODULE-IDENITY, OBJECT-IDENTITY, NOTIFICATION-TYPE, 
        OBJECT-GROUP, NOTIFICATION-GROUP, MODULE-COMPLIANCE and the 
        improved OBJECT-TYPE macro (as of SNMPv2).</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Updated MIB syntax with textual conventions</title>
        <text>The MIB file parser can now handle the 
        TEXTUAL-CONVENTION macro type.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>API changes breaking backwards compability</title>
        <text>The MIB class was renamed to Mib and several new 
        methods were added to allow easy access to the information 
        in the MIB file. Some old methods were also renamed to better
        match the new methods.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Improved code style</title>
        <text>All the source code has been reindented to use four (4)
        spaces, and various minor code style improvements have been 
        made in the source tree.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Improved API documentation</title>
        <text>The API documentation has been somewhat improved by 
        adding package descriptions and improving the class 
        comments.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added MIB example code</title>
        <text>An example class has been added to demonstrate how the 
        library can be used.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added initial test cases</title>
        <text>Some initial test cases have been added, making 
        regression testing easier. Much work is still missing on the 
        test cases, though.</text>
      </item>
    </list>


    <h1>Version 1.0 (2002-08-14):</h1>

    <list>
      <item>
        <title>First public release</title>
        <text>The first public release of this library.</text>
      </item>
    </list>

  </body>
</doc>
