<doc>
  <head>
    <title>Mibble Version Information</title>
  </head>

  <body>

    <h1>Version <param name="version"/> (<param name="date"/>):</h1>

    <list>
      <item>
        <title>Changed missing SMI import from error to warning</title>
        <text>Some MIB files lacks a proper SMI MIB import, previously causing
        a parse error due to unresolved symbols. This has now been fixed by
        silently importing RFC1155-SMI when no other SNMP SMI module has been
        imported, causing each of these errors to be reported as a warning
        instead. <ref bug="7113" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Fixed NPE issue when checking for null directories</title>
        <text>The <code>MibLoader</code> class didn't properly handle null
        directories in the <code>hasDir</code> method. This caused an NPE
        when attempting to load MIB files from the current directory without
        using a directory prefix on the file name. <ref bug="26146" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Fixed omitted character in extract from error MIBs</title>
        <text>The first character in each MIB line extracted and printed in
        error messages was previously omitted, causing the error location to
        be off by one character. This error was introduced when correcting
        <ref bug="16252" /> in version 2.7. <ref bug="26150" /></text>
      </item>
    </list>


    <h1>Version 2.9.1 (2009-04-04):</h1>

    <list>
      <item>
        <title>Fixed issue with input streams not closed on error</title>
        <text>The <code>MibLoader</code> class didn't properly close the
        input file streams if a parse exception was encountered. Thanks to
        Masanori Sekido for reporting this. <ref bug="26082" /></text>
      </item>
    </list>


    <h1>Version 2.9 (2009-03-19):</h1>

    <list>
      <item>
        <title>Added complete comment extraction and printing</title>
        <text>The comments from all MIB constructs are now extracted and
        stored in the respective objects. No comments are ever lost, but
        may be assigned to a parent object in the parsed data structure.
        The <code>MibWriter</code> pretty-printer has also been extended
        to print all available comments. Thanks to Cisco for requesting
        and financing this work. <ref bug="18844" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added new convenience methods in MibLoader class</title>
        <text>The <code>MibLoader</code> class has been improved with a
        number of new convenience methods to enable improved access to
        the MIB search path and easier unloading of all MIBs (freeing
        the memory used).</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Improved parsing speed significantly</title>
        <text>The <code>MibLoader</code> class is now much faster when
        parsing MIB files, mostly due to speedups in Grammatica 1.5 but
        also thanks to a number of speed optimizations in Mibble
        proper. Make sure to reuse the same <code>MibLoader</code>
        instance when parsing multiple MIB files for optimum effect of
        these improvements.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Improved the Mibble Browser user interface</title>
        <text>The Mibble Browser test application has been improved in
        various ways to make it easier to work with. It is now also
        packaged into a separate jar file for easy startup by double-click
        on most platforms. Thanks to Richard E. Brown for a long list of
        suggested UI improvements.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Changed some bundled IANA and IETF MIB files</title>
        <text>A number of IANA and IETF MIB files bundled with Mibble have
        been added or updated to match those distributed in
        <code>libsmi</code> 0.4.8 (2008-04-18). Thanks to Elyes
        Lehtihet for the reminder. <ref bug="19905" /> &amp;
        <ref bug="24435" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Changed bundled SNMP API to Westhawk SNMP 6.0</title>
        <text>The MibbleBrowser SNMP support has been updated to use the
        newer version 6.0 of the Westhawk SNMP stack. This fixes a few
        issue with SNMP context ID. Thanks to Vincent Lane for reporting
        this. <ref bug="24385" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Changed startup scripts for better auto-detection</title>
        <text>The various shell startup scripts for Linux, Mac and Windows
        have been updated to have better auto-detection of the location
        of Java and the application itself. Thanks to Richard E. Brown for
        commenting on this.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Fixed syntax error for inline ASN.1 comments</title>
        <text>When an inline ASN.1 comment was ended on the same line and
        followed by another construct, a syntax error would result. The
        ASN.1 parser in Mibble has now been fixed to handled inline comments
        properly. Thanks to Karl Weber for reporting this.
        <ref bug="22841" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Fixed NPE when parsing unresolved referenced types</title>
        <text>When a textual convention or similar contained an unresolved
        type reference, a NullPointerException could occur when using the
        defined type elsewhere (like in a <code>SEQUENCE</code> type). This
        has now been corrected and a new reference error is shown instead.
        Thanks to Markus Barchfeld for reporting this.
        <ref bug="18843" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Fixed missing padding for some hex and binary constants</title>
        <text>After <ref bug="17834" /> there were still some cases where
        padding would be removed from specified hexadecimal and binary
        values in MIB files. A fix has now been implemented that takes all
        size constraint values into consideration, not just the lower
        bound. Thanks to M. S. Thiraviyakumar for reporting this and
        providing a fix. <ref bug="22854" /></text>
      </item>
    </list>


    <h1>Version 2.8 (2007-01-10):</h1>

    <list>
      <item>
        <title>Added default ccitt and joint-iso-ccitt symbols</title>
        <text>The <code>ccitt</code> and <code>joint-iso-ccitt</code> OID
        symbols have been added to the default context. The
        <code>zeroDotZero</code> and similar symbols are now also
        automatically connected to the correct root symbol. Thanks to Bernd
        Sorgenfrei for reporting this. <ref bug="16827" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added enumeration comment extraction and printing</title>
        <text>The MIB comments around enumeration or bit set value are now
        extracted and stored in the respective symbols. The
        <code>MibWriter</code> pretty-printer has also been extended to
        print these comments. Thanks to Eshwar Yedavalli and Cisco for
        requesting and financing this feature. <ref bug="17879" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added symbolic bit set value printing</title>
        <text>The bit set values are now printed with symbolic names
        instead of numbers by the <code>MibWriter</code> pretty-printer.
        <ref bug="17835" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Changed some bundled IANA MIB files</title>
        <text>A number of IANA MIB files bundled with Mibble have been added
        or updated. These are <code>IANAifType-MIB</code>,
        <code>IANA-PRINTER-MIB</code>, <code>IANA-ITU-ALARM-TC-MIB</code>
        and <code>IANA-IPPM-METRICS-REGISTRY-MIB</code>. Thanks to Bernd
        Sorgenfrei for reporting this and providing a pointer to the new
        versions. <ref bug="16826" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Changed some bundled IETF MIB files</title>
        <text>A number of IETF MIB files bundled with Mibble have been added
        or updated. These are <code>INET-ADDRESS-MIB</code>,
        <code>IP-FORWARD-MIB</code>, <code>SNMP-USM-AES-MIB</code>,
        <code>TCP-MIB</code> and <code>UDP-MIB</code>.
        <ref bug="16826" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Fixed incorrect Mib.getRootSymbol method</title>
        <text>The <code>Mib.getRootSymbol()</code> method returned an invalid
        root symbol in some cases and was unreliable. Thanks to Bernd
        Sorgenfrei for reporting and fixing this. <ref bug="16824" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Fixed duplicate loading of implicitly loaded MIBs</title>
        <text>Due to a bug in <code>MibLoader</code> that was introduced in
        version 2.7, some MIBs could be loaded several times. This caused
        higher loading times, more memory usage and duplicate MIBs being
        returned by <code>MibLoader.getAllMibs()</code>. Thanks to Bernd
        Sorgenfrei for reporting and fixing this. <ref bug="16825" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Fixed parse error on references in AGENT-CAPABILITIES</title>
        <text>A parse error was thrown when using symbolic references in the
        <code>DEFVAL</code>, <code>SYNTAX</code> or
        <code>CREATION-REQUIRES</code> clauses inside an
        <code>AGENT-CAPABILITIES</code> macro. This has now been corrected so
        that the correct symbol name references are available. Thanks to
        Eshwar Yedavalli and Cisco for reporting this and financing the bug fix.
        <ref bug="17705" /> &amp; <ref bug="17943" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Fixed incorrect printing of binary and hexadecimal values</title>
        <text>The <code>MibWriter</code> class printed binary and hexadecimal
        values with their shortest possible length, omitting any required
        zero (0) padding. The code now considers the defining type to determine
        the required amount of padding. Thanks to Eshwar Yedavalli and Cisco
        for reporting this and financing the bug fix.<ref bug="17834" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Fixed bad value error for some SNMP operations</title>
        <text>When attempting a <code>SET</code> operation on a counter or a
        gauge value, the <code>MibbleBrowser</code> would return a "bad value
        error". This has now been corrected by using the proper WestHawk SNMP
        calls. Thanks to Paul Faid for finding and fixing this.
        <ref bug="18591" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Fixed incorrect value validation for size constraints</title>
        <text>The <code>SizeConstraint.isCompatible(MibValue)</code> method
        always returned false, regardless of the value provided. This has now
        been corrected, so that the actual length of an octet string value is
        checked. Thanks to Paul Faid for reporting this.
        <ref bug="18741" /></text>
      </item>
    </list>


    <h1>Version 2.7 (2006-05-28):</h1>

    <list>
      <item>
        <title>Added MIB loader support for loading from a single file</title>
        <text>The <code>MibLoader</code> class now properly supports loading
        MIB modules from a single file even if the modules have references
        to each other. Previously it was only possible to load multiple MIBs
        in a single file if the referenced MIB modules were placed at the top
        of the file. Thanks to Ted Kaczmarek for suggesting this.
        <ref bug="16417" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added detection of explicitly vs implicitly loaded MIBs</title>
        <text>The <code>Mib</code> class now contains a new
        <code>isLoaded()</code> method to enable easy separation between
        explicitly and implicitly loaded MIBs. The latter are MIB modules
        that have been loaded due to an import declaration. The MibblePrinter
        application has also been updated to print all explicitly loaded
        MIBs instead of just the first MIB module in each file.
        <ref bug="16419" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added numeric OID value cache for improved performance</title>
        <text>The <code>ObjectIdentifierValue</code> class now caches the
        result of the <code>toString()</code> method in order to improve
        performance. Thanks to Mohamed Ben-Hedi Sghaier for providing a fix
        for this. <ref bug="16418" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added simple method for finding MIB importers</title>
        <text>The <code>Mib.getImportingMibs()</code> method has been added
        to provide a simple API for finding MIB importers. If the returned
        list is empty, the MIB is safe for unloading.
        <ref bug="16543" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added easy access to the root object identifier</title>
        <text>The <code>MibLoader.getRootOid()</code> method has been added
        to make it easier to access the root object identifier value (i.e.
        the predefined <code>iso</code> value. <ref bug="16544" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added easy lookup of referenced textual conventions</title>
        <text>The <code>SnmpTextualConvention.findReference()</code> method
        has been added to enable easy lookup of referenced textual conventions.
        <ref bug="16643" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Changed toString() to print enumeration names</title>
        <text>The <code>BitSetType</code> and <code>IntegerType</code> classes
        have been modified to print both enumeration names and values in the
        <code>toString()</code> method. Both the MibbleBrowser and
        MibblePrinter applications are affected by this, making it easier to
        interpret SNMP results returned. <ref bug="16420" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Fixed issue with MIB unloading not removing references</title>
        <text>The <code>MibLoader.unload()</code> method didn't properly
        remove all references to the MIB as the object identifier tree
        remained linked. This has now been corrected so that an unloaded
        MIB will be completely removed and eligible for garbage collection.
        Thanks to Eshwar Yedavalli for reporting this.
        <ref bug="16285" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Fixed IndexOutOfBoundsException for some error logs</title>
        <text>When loading MIB files with invalid line termination sequences
        the <code>MibLoaderLog</code> couldn't properly locate and load the
        context line for any errors. This has been fixed so that only
        linefeed (LF, 0x0A) is counted in line numbers when reading context
        lines. Thanks to Ted Kaczmarek for reporting this.
        <ref bug="16252" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Fixed parse error for some ASCII control characters</title>
        <text>When loading MIB files with some unsupported ASCII control
        characters, the parser failed with a parse exception. The parser has
        now been modified to ignore a number of common control codes in ASCII,
        such as form-feed, vertical tab, substitute and others. Thanks to
        Gary Pientka for reporting this. <ref bug="16681" /></text>
      </item>
    </list>


    <h1>Version 2.6 (2005-12-10):</h1>

    <list>
      <item>
        <title>Added a MIB pretty printer</title>
        <text>A SMIv2 pretty printer has been added to Mibble. It can
        be accessed either with the <code>MibblePrinter</code>
        utility application, or directly with the new
        <code>MibWriter</code> class. Thanks to Cisco for financing this
        work. <ref bug="14638" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added new Mib convenience method</title>
        <text>The <code>Mib</code> class in the Mibble API has been
        improved by the addition of a new <code>getRootSymbol()</code>
        method for retrieving the root value symbol.
        <ref bug="14831" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added new MibValueSymbol convenience methods</title>
        <text>The <code>MibValueSymbol</code> class in the Mibble API
        has been improved by the addition of new methods for
        retrieving child symbols. This will facilitate some accesses
        that could previously be a bit cumbersome to write.
        <ref bug="13151" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added MIB import information retrieval</title>
        <text>The <code>Mib</code> class now contains a method
        <code>getAllImports()</code> that allows retrieval of the
        import declarations for a MIB. The class
        <code>MibImport</code> has also been added to the public API.
        <ref bug="14637" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added module and symbol comment retrieval</title>
        <text>The <code>Mib</code> and <code>MibSymbol</code> classes
        in the Mibble API have been improved by allowing the
        retrieval of MIB file comments. This will enable full access
        to any ASN.1 comment text that were previously ignored.
        <ref bug="14636" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added macro symbol retrieval</title>
        <text>The <code>MibMacroSymbol</code> class has been added to
        the Mibble API, so that there is now three types of symbols.
        This will enable full access to all imported symbols.
        <ref bug="14727" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added SnmpCompliance type separation API</title>
        <text>The <code>SnmpCompliance</code> class didn't allow an
        application to distinguish between GROUP and OBJECT
        compliances easily. A new method <code>isGroup()</code> has
        been added to the API so that this is now possible.
        <ref bug="14765" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added SMI version number retrieval</title>
        <text>The <code>Mib</code> class now has a new method
        <code>getSmiVersion</code> that returns the SMI version that
        was used for defining the MIB. This makes it easier to
        perform different validations for different MIB:s.
        <ref bug="15078" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added hashCode() and compareTo() implementations</title>
        <text>The <code>hashCode()</code> method has been added to
        all classes implementing <code>equals()</code>. Also, the
        <code>MibValue</code> class is now <code>Comparable</code>
        making it easier to compare values. <ref bug="13222" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Changed to support IMPLIED in index lists</title>
        <text>A new class <code>SnmpIndex</code> has been added to
        encapsulate an index type or value. The method
        <code>SnmpObjectType.getIndex()</code> has been modified to
        return a list of these new index objects, which will break
        existing code using this method. <ref bug="10870" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Changed several SNMP text returning methods</title>
        <text>The <code>getDescription()</code> and similar methods
        in several SNMP type classes have been modified to remove a
        cleaner version of the text (with indentation removed). This
        was introduced in 2.5 for one field, but has now been
        expanded to more fields. Use the corresponding
        <code>getUnformattedXXX()</code> methods for the original
        behaviour. <ref bug="14728" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Changed enumeration symbol ordering</title>
        <text>The <code>getAllSymbols()</code> method in the
        <code>BitSetType</code> and <code>IntegerType</code> classes
        has been modified to return the symbol list in the same order
        as the symbols appears in the MIB file. The internal list
        representation was changed to <code>LinkedHashMap</code>,
        so JDK 1.4 is now required. <ref bug="13221" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Changed OID validation for mismatched names</title>
        <text>When two OID:s used different names for the same
        component, this was previously considered a MIB loading error.
        The error message for this has been clarified and it is now
        just a warning instead of an error. <ref bug="13309" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Changed binary and hexadecimal value classes</title>
        <text>Two new <code>MibValue</code> classes have been
        introduced to store binary and hexadecimal numbers. Both
        inherit the old <code>NumberValue</code> class, but modify
        the implementation of <code>toString()</code> to print the
        value in the correct ASN.1 representation. This might break
        old code, but the old behaviour is available by using
        <code>value.toObject().toString()</code> instead. Thanks to
        Andreas Schönbach for suggesting this. <ref bug="15139" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Fixed NullPointerException on some invalid OID:s</title>
        <text>When two OID:s used different names for the same
        component, a NullPointerException was thrown when defining
        value symbols using the second OID. This has been fixed so
        that type or value validation errors should no longer be able
        to cause NPE:s in later stages. <ref bug="13309" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Fixed parse error for hex values in enumerations</title>
        <text>When using binary or hexadecimal values as integer
        enumerated values, the parser displayed a syntax error. This
        has now been fixed, so that both binary and hexadecimal
        values are allowed. Thanks to Andreas Schönbach for reporting
        this. <ref bug="15027" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Fixed issue with MIB file not being set in loader log</title>
        <text>The MIB file was sometime set to null in the
        <code>MibLoaderLog</code> entries. This could cause
        NullPointerExceptions when attepting to print an error or
        a warning message. This has been fixed so that NPE:s will no
        longer occur in these cases and the MIB loader should now
        properly set the MIB file in all log entries.
        <ref bug="10824" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Fixed size constraint type validity checking</title>
        <text>The <code>SizeConstraint</code> didn't accept the
        <code>StringType</code> as compatible, which has now been
        fixed. All constraints are now also checked for validity
        upon type initialization. <ref bug="10823" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Fixed MibbleBrowser file chooser directory</title>
        <text>The file chooser dialog in the MibbleBrowser always
        started in the user home directory instead of the current
        directory. This has now been fixed and the application also
        remembers where the directory where the last MIB was loaded.
        <ref bug="11767" /></text>
      </item>
    </list>


    <h1>Version 2.5 (2004-10-26):</h1>

    <list>
      <item>
        <title>Added SNMPv2c &amp; SNMPv3 to the MIB browser</title>
        <text>The MIB browser application has been updated in a
        variety of ways, adding support for SNMPv2c &amp; SNMPv3,
        command-line MIB loading and improved tree walking. The
        graphical interface has also been totally reworked so it
        should now both look better and provide more visual feedback.
        The browser is now also available in the commercial version.
        <ref bug="10732" /> &amp; <ref bug="10748" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added support for multiple MIB modules in a single file</title>
        <text>The library now supports loading multiple MIB modules
        from a single file, as required per the ASN.1 standard. It
        is still strongly recommended to place each MIB module in its
        own file however. Thanks to Frank Fock for reporting this.
        <ref bug="10261" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added new base class for SNMP macro types</title>
        <text>Added a new <code>SnmpType</code> class as a new base
        class for all the SNMP macro types. So far the API it
        provides is rather minimal, but it makes it easier to
        distinguish between ASN.1 types and SNMP macro types. Thanks
        to Thomas Åhlén for suggesting this.
        <ref bug="10731" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added new convenience methods to some classes</title>
        <text>The <code>MibValueSymbol</code>,
        <code>ObjectIdentifierValue</code> and <code>SnmpAccess</code>
        classes in the Mibble API have been improved by the addition
        of new methods. This will facilitate some searches or tests
        that could previously be a bit cumbersome to write.
        <ref bug="10634" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added OID tree printing to MibblePrinter</title>
        <text>The <code>MibblePrinter</code> test application has been
        extended to allow several input files and now also contains an
        option to print the complete OID tree. Thanks to Thomas Åhlén
        for the original idea. <ref bug="10651" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Changed semantics of getDescription() method</title>
        <text>The <code>getDescription()</code> method has been
        changed to return a cleaner version of the description text.
        All unneeded indentation is removed and tab characters are
        now replaced with spaces. The old semantics is available from
        the new <code>getUnformattedDescription()</code> method.
        <ref bug="10790" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Changed the location of the bundled MIB files</title>
        <text>The MIB files bundled with Mibble have been moved to
        a separate JAR-file. This makes it easier to replace, update
        or remove them without modifying other parts of Mibble. As a
        result of this, the parser JAR-file has also been renamed.
        <ref bug="10648" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Changed the bundled MIB file content</title>
        <text>The MIB files bundled with Mibble have been updated.
        Many new IANA and IETF MIB files have been added and quite a
        few existing MIBs have been modified to the corresponding
        latest version. Thanks to Thomas Åhlén for pointing this out.
        <ref bug="10647" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Fixed issue with OIDs not being merged properly</title>
        <text>The OID tree was previously missing child components
        (symbols) in some cases. This could occur when the same OID
        was defined in two MIB files, something commonly used to
        avoid circular imports. Now all the OIDs are properly merged
        to any depth, making sure that none are ignored. Thanks to
        Thomas Åhlén for finding this. <ref bug="9962" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Fixed issue with MIBs being loaded as often as imported</title>
        <text>Previously it was possible that some base MIBs, that
        were used in several places, got loaded several times by the
        <code>MibLoader</code>. This didn't affect the correctness of
        the results, but wasted time and memory. The MibLoader has
        now been corrected to avoid this and therefore loads many MIB
        files faster. <ref bug="10673" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Fixed OID searching in Mib.getSymbolByOid()</title>
        <text>The Mib.getSymbolByOid() method handled OIDs with table
        indices erroneously due to a conceptual error. This has now
        been corrected, but has unfortunately led to a slight API
        change, removing the exactMatch parameter in the method call.
        <ref bug="10765" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Fixed documentation terminology and feature list</title>
        <text>Various pieces of documentation previously used the
        wrong terminology for SMIv1 and SMIv2, which has now been
        corrected. Also, the feature list has been updated to be a
        bit more informative, although documentation will primarily
        be added to the website from now on. Thanks to David T.
        Perkins and Frank Fock for pointing out these shortcomings.
        <ref bug="10170" /> &amp; <ref bug="10262" /></text>
      </item>
    </list>


    <h1>Version 2.4 (2004-05-27):</h1>

    <list>
      <item>
        <title>Relicensed to GNU GPL</title>
        <text>Most of the source code has been relicensed to GNU GPL,
        removing the previous linking exception. As an alternative to
        using the GNU GPL license, a non-exclusive commercial license
        for Mibble can be purchased. A FAQ explaining the implications
        of this is available on the Mibble web site.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added simpler OID to symbol lookup</title>
        <text>A new method <code>getSymbolByOid</code> has been added
        to the <code>Mib</code> class to simplify the lookup of
        symbols from OIDs. This method handles table row number inside
        OIDs, that the <code>getSymbolByValue</code> method couldn't
        handle. <ref bug="9117" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Changed MIB loader to search inside files</title>
        <text>If the <code>MibLoader</code> fails to locate a MIB file
        based on its name, it will now resort to read the first few
        lines from all files in the search path until a matching MIB
        name is found. Opening many files may be a potential
        performance bottleneck, so it is still recommended best
        practice to name MIB files according to the MIB module name.
        <ref bug="8862" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Changed some symbol import errors to warnings</title>
        <text>Missing imports for symbols where the other symbols are
        imported from the right MIB is no longer an error. A recovery
        mechanism has been added searching for an undefined symbol in
        all imported MIB files, issuing a warning instead of an error
        if the symbol was found. <ref bug="8863" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Changed to a simpler Ant build file</title>
        <text>The <code>build.xml</code> file for Apache Ant
        distributed with Mibble has been simplified. It now also
        contains some documentation to make it easier to use.
        <ref bug="9097" /></text>
      </item>
    </list>


    <h1>Version 2.3 (2004-03-10):</h1>

    <list>
      <item>
        <title>Added graphical MIB browser</title>
        <text>A graphical MIB browser has been added that allows for
        easy viewing of a MIB contents, while also sending SNMP
        requests for objects. Many thanks to Watsh Rajneesh and HP
        India for contributing the code. Thanks also to Charles F.
        Schatz for providing an alternate implementation.
        <ref bug="4366" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added shell scripts for launching utilities</title>
        <text>Shell scripts for Unix and Windows have been added
        for launching the Mibble utility programs. The original
        scripts were contributed by Watsh Rajneesh.
        <ref bug="6961" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added API for loading MIBs from more sources</title>
        <text>Added new <code>addResourceDir()</code> method to the
        MibLoader class, allowing usage of the Java ClassLoader for
        locating and loading MIB files. Also, new
        <code>load(URL)</code> and <code>load(Reader)</code> methods
        has been added to simplify loading MIBs from other sources.
        The MibblePrinter and MibbleValidator programs have also been
        extended to also support URLs. Thanks to Yun Freund for
        suggesting this. <ref bug="7746" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added support for unloading MIBs</title>
        <text>Added new <code>unload()</code> methods to the MibLoader
        class. It is now possible to remove references to a single MIB
        without losing the references to all MIBs.
        <ref bug="7616" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added method for retrieving all OID children</title>
        <text>Added new <code>getAllChildren()</code> method to the
        ObjectIdentifierValue class. This makes it easier to retrieve
        all OID children at once. <ref bug="8046" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Modified the API for MibLoader.load() slightly</title>
        <text>The various <code>load()</code> methods in the MibLoader
        class have had their API slightly modified. They are now
        declared to throw IOException instead of the previous
        FileNotFoundException in order to accomodate the new
        <code>load(URL)</code> and <code>load(Reader)</code> methods.
        <ref bug="7746" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Modified OID child ordering</title>
        <text>The ObjectIdentifierValue child ordering has been
        changed from undefined to numerical order. The new
        implementation is actually faster than the previous one, due
        to more clever object comparison than previously used. 
        <ref bug="8090" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Fixed issue with not always finding loaded MIBs</title>
        <text>Previously when loading named MIBs, the search path was
        first used to locate the MIB file. If the MIB file couldn't be
        found in the path, an exception is thrown. The MibLoader has
        now been extended to first check the loaded MIB names, thereby
        making it possible to manually load MIB files not adhering to
        the MIB file naming standard. Thanks to Zemian Deng for
        pointing this out. <ref bug="6959" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Fixed problem loading MIBs from current directory</title>
        <text>When loading MIB files from the current directory with
        the MibblePrinter or MibbleValidator application, the
        directory wasn't correctly added to the MibLoader path. This
        has now been fixed, so MIB imports now works correctly even
        for file names without a directory portion. 
        <ref bug="6528" /></text>
      </item>
    </list>


    <h1>Version 2.2 (2003-11-03):</h1>

    <list>
      <item>
        <title>Added support for ASN1.1 type tags</title>
        <text>All primitive type now have default ASN.1 type tags and
        these may also be overridden by tags in the MIB files. New
        methods <code>isPrimitive()</code> and <code>getTag()</code>
        has been added to <code>MibType</code>. Thanks to Sudhir
        Khurana for pointing this out. <ref bug="5001" /> &amp; 
        <ref bug="5003" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added validation of sequence elements</title>
        <text>Sequence element names previously weren't validated
        against the containing MIB. This has now been changed so
        that sequence elements inside an OBJECT TYPE will be looked
        up in the MIB. If no symbol with that name could be found,
        a new default symbol is created. Thanks to Charles F. Schatz
        for finding and reporting this. <ref bug="5904" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added access to referenced type and value symbols</title>
        <text>When resolving type and value references, the
        referenced symbol name was previously lost and only the type
        or value information was extracted. This has been fixed and
        new convenience methods <code>isReferenceTo()</code> in the
        MibType and MibValue classes have been added. Thanks to
        Charles F. Schatz for suggesting this.
        <ref bug="6112" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added a number of missing accessor methods</title>
        <text>Several primitive types lacked accessor methods for
        retrieving the constraints, defined values and similar. The
        MIB symbols lacked a getMib() method. These accessor methods
        have now been added. <ref bug="5007" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Changed the logging API</title>
        <text>The logging API was simplified by removal of the log
        printing classes. The same functionality is now present
        directly in the <code>MibLoaderLog</code> class. A new method
        <code>entries()</code> allows direct retrieval of all log
        entries from the log, providing a more generic approach than
        the previous one. <ref bug="6116" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Improved Javadoc API documentation</title>
        <text>The Javadoc API documentation has been generally
        improved in various places. References to appropriate RFC
        documents have been added along with initial package
        overviews. <ref bug="6155" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Updated to version 1.4 of Grammatica</title>
        <text>The Grammatica library distributed with Mibble has been
        updated to version 1.4 (from 1.3). The build file has been
        simplified as a result of this. <ref bug="5000" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Removed some previously public methods</title>
        <text>A number of internal methods were previously public
        although there was no need for them to be. This has been
        fixed by making them private or package protected. Code that
        called these methods should be modified to use the correct
        public counterparts.</text>
      </item>
    </list>


    <h1>Version 2.1 (2003-08-22):</h1>

    <list>
      <item>
        <title>Corrected MIB symbol value search</title>
        <text>Searching for MIB symbols by value never returned any
        results in the previous version. Thanks to Nigel Mellor for
        finding and fixing this. <ref bug="4893" /></text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Updated to version 1.3 of Grammatica</title>
        <text>The Grammatica library distributed with Mibble has been
        updated to version 1.3 (from 1.2). Minor changes have been
        made to the parser to accomodate this.
        <ref bug="4903" /></text>
      </item>
    </list>


    <h1>Version 2.0 (2003-07-19):</h1>

    <list>
      <item>
        <title>Complete rewrite with API and name change</title>
        <text>The project has been renamed to Mibble, and the library
        has been completely rewritten from scratch. The API:s have
        also been replaced to correct a number of serious flaws in
        the previous design.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added complete support for SNMPv2 and SNMPv3</title>
        <text>All types and constructs in SNMPv2 and SNMPv3 are now
        supported.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added a real MIB import mechanism</title>
        <text>Symbol imports are now handled by reading and parsing
        the MIB file. Standard IANA and IETF MIB files have been
        added to the JAR library, in order to always have these
        imports available.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added full access to all type information</title>
        <text>All of the type information can now be easily accessed
        through methods in the type classes.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added syntactical and semantical error recovery</title>
        <text>The MIB parser now attempts to recover from errors in
        the MIB file. All encountered errors are available after the
        parsing is complete. This change was made available by using
        Grammatica instead of JavaCC to generate the parser.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added warnings for wrong identifier case</title>
        <text>A warning is now issued if the first character in a
        type identifier is lower-case, or if the first character in a
        value identifier is upper-case.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added HTML release notes</title>
        <text>The release notes are now generated to both text and
        HTML format from an XML representation.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Changed parser generator to Grammatica</title>
        <text>The JavaCC parser generator has been replaced with
        Grammatica. This was done as JavaCC isn't free software, and
        Grammatica was chosen as it provides a simple grammar syntax,
        a decent parsing and analysis framework, and very high
        quality error handling.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Removed the old symbol tree model</title>
        <text>The symbol tree model has been removed as it was not
        compatible with the new API:s.</text>
      </item>
    </list>


    <h1>Version 1.2 (2003-03-27):</h1>

    <list>
      <item>
        <title>Relicensing to GPL + linking exception</title>
        <text>Relicensed all the source code to GPL plus a linking
        exception. See the new LICENSE.txt file for details.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Removed JavaCC requirement from Ant build file</title>
        <text>Removed the strict dependency of JavaCC from Ant build
        file (build.xml). The JavaCC parser generator will be replaced
        in a future version of the library.</text>
      </item>
    </list>


    <h1>Version 1.1 (2003-01-06):</h1>

    <list>
      <item>
        <title>Updated MIB syntax to SNMPv2</title>
        <text>The MIB file parser can now handle several new macros,
        such as MODULE-IDENITY, OBJECT-IDENTITY, NOTIFICATION-TYPE,
        OBJECT-GROUP, NOTIFICATION-GROUP, MODULE-COMPLIANCE and the
        improved OBJECT-TYPE macro (as of SNMPv2).</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Updated MIB syntax with textual conventions</title>
        <text>The MIB file parser can now handle the
        TEXTUAL-CONVENTION macro type.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>API changes breaking backwards compability</title>
        <text>The MIB class was renamed to Mib and several new
        methods were added to allow easy access to the information
        in the MIB file. Some old methods were also renamed to better
        match the new methods.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Improved code style</title>
        <text>All the source code has been reindented to use four (4)
        spaces, and various minor code style improvements have been
        made in the source tree.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Improved API documentation</title>
        <text>The API documentation has been somewhat improved by
        adding package descriptions and improving the class
        comments.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added MIB example code</title>
        <text>An example class has been added to demonstrate how the
        library can be used.</text>
      </item>

      <item>
        <title>Added initial test cases</title>
        <text>Some initial test cases have been added, making
        regression testing easier. Much work is still missing on the
        test cases, though.</text>
      </item>
    </list>


    <h1>Version 1.0 (2002-08-14):</h1>

    <list>
      <item>
        <title>First public release</title>
        <text>The first public release of this library.</text>
      </item>
    </list>

  </body>
</doc>
